SOLAR ECLIPSE AT WAKOR AUGUST 18 , 2411 B.E.
ON THE FIRST WAXING DAY OF THE NINTH LUNAR MONTH
Honor to the Blessed One
The Exalted One The Fully Enlightened One
The Exalted One
The Fully Enlightened One
I have to go , Nak .
Mak ...
The story of Nak 's ghostly spirit
is long believed to be true .
Legend has it that Nak of Phra Khanong
was once a devoted wife ,
highly loyal to her husband .
Even in death ,
her love and devotion
continued to live on .
Her spirit
still lingered there ,
waiting for her husband to come home .
Prik !
Help !
Anybody ! Help ! Injured soldier over here !
Prik !
Mak !
Nak ...
Will Mak be alright ?
Father , please tell me .
I 'm so worried .
Mak will be afflicted ...
rather critically .
But you don 't have to worry as his fate is still going strong .
That 's a relief .
But I 'm still concerned about his well-being .
Is there any way to lessen his misfortune ?
Prepare offerings for a monk .
Then I 'll pray to atone his karma from those whom he 's done wrong .
Always carry this amulet with you .
It protects you from evil spirits .
A pregnant woman like yourself should carry one .
Anyway , how far along are you ?
Almost four months .
I do feel sorry for you , Nak .
BANGKOK
THE 8th WANING DAY OF THE 2nd LUNAR MONTH , 2412 B.E.
Help !
Help ! Help !
He 's in critical condition .
It 's beyond what I can do now .
I 'm afraid he 's going to die .
Only Somdet can help .
We still have to wait for him to return .
I must go now .
Nak ...
Mak , it 's me .
Prik ...
Mak ...
- Mak ... - Prik ...
Mak ... Mak ... Mak ...
Yuean ! Press carefully , you fool !
Yuean ! How 's she doing ?
- Just stay still . - Nak , hold on . It 'll be alright .
Damn it , Yuean ! You keep the fire going !
Don 't let it get extinguished !
Keep going . Keep going .
Why is this so hard ?
Why are you blocking the doorway ?
She 's having a hard time already . That 's a bad omen .
Prik !
Mak ...
How long has he been here ?
Yesterday evening
the doctor at Tha Tian brought him here .
Quite fatal it seems .
Come on , hurry up !
Sadhu .
Hang in there .
Drink this sacred water .
It helps you deliver with ease . Yes . Drink it . There you go .
Um ! What the hell are you doing ? Go open the windows !
Windows must be open during labor .
Oh dear ! Why is it so hard this time ?
Looks like I have to cut it open .
And the sublime Leaders Stand firmly upon my head
The Buddha is upon my head
Nak .
Hold on . It 's going to hurt .
Together with his army and vehicles ...
Mak !
How is he , Novice ?
- Is he getting better ? - He 's a little better .
But stable .
Good .
THONBURI , THE 15th WAXING DAY OF THE 11th LUNAR MONTH , 2412 B.E.
Mak ... Mak ...
Oh , Novice . How can I help you ?
Somdet wants to see you . He 's waiting in his rectory .
Alright .
How are you feeling ?
Seems like you restored your health .
I 'm doing fine .
I made it through thanks to you and your kindness .
Fate is such a strange thing .
Some seem like they are dying but survive .
Some die all of a sudden without a sign .
That is , what 's certain is uncertain .
Since you 're in good health now ,
I suggest you enter monkhood .
So , your sins and karma will be lessened .
What do you think ?
You 're worried about your family you left behind .
Yes .
I have a wife back at Phra Khanong .
She 's far along in her pregnancy . She must have given birth by now .
It 's just two of them . I don 't know if they 're doing alright .
I 'm so worried .
So , I think I 'd better go home .
Later on ,
I 'll come back to get ordained and serve you .
Then that 's up to you .
But no matter what happens ,
keep yourself together .
Everything comes as a result of karma .
Let go of attachment ,
or else , it brings you sufferings .
Nak !
- Mak ! - Nak !
Mak !
Nak , I 'm home .
You look so worn and thin .
You went to battle . Didn 't the army feed you well ?
Basically , lived on chilies and salt .
Sometimes ,
they didn 't even send provisions .
We had to dig for some yams to eat .
It was really difficult , my dear .
And the wilderness was dreadful there .
Many died from jungle fever .
Then cholera spread widely .
So many soldiers lost their lives .
What about you ? Did anything happen to you ?
During the fight ,
I was slashed in the chest .
Almost didn 't make it .
Fortunately , Somdet Wat Rakhang saved my life .
Otherwise ,
I would have died .
But poor Prik !
He 's gone too soon .
What ? Prik is dead ?
His head was almost cut off .
He died right in front of me .
His body was burnt like he was nobody .
Oh , his poor soul .
I almost forgot .
His wife , Pad , doesn 't know yet .
I have to tell her .
What ? Right now ?
Yes .
But you just arrived .
Just get some rest .
I 'll go tell her myself .
Daeng is still little .
How can you take him out there ?
I have to .
He 's such a mommy 's boy .
Since he was born ,
we 've never separated .
I 'd rather have that one in your mouth .
No ! Don 't !
No ! You naughty !
Betel from your mouth is so sweet , my love .
Hey !
- Mak ! - Mak !
- Don 't you feel embarrassed ? - Yeah , getting intimate out here .
Sharing betel ? Isn 't it disgusting ?
- She 's running away . Follow her . - You bastards !
You sneak up on me ?
Well then , if I can 't crack your head open ,
don 't call me a man ! Prik ! Um !
Prik ! Um !
Don 't you run !
Come and get me !
Imagine I 'm Nak .
Come on ! Real men don 't run away like that !
Let me get some blood out of your head .
Um !
Prik !
Where are you ?
Please help me ...
Prik !
- Prik ! - Mak ...
Prik , please don 't die !
Mak !
- Mak ! - Prik !
Oeb !
Are you home ?
It 's me , Mak .
Oh , Nak !
You scared me !
I didn 't hear you coming .
I 've been waiting for you at home .
But you didn 't show up . And I couldn 't find you anywhere .
I was afraid
you 'd leave me again .
Nak , why would you say such a thing ?
I will never do that .
I just came to get some nipa leaves .
I 'm going to make a woven-fish mobile for Daeng .
Come on . Let 's go back home .
Um ! Um !
Um !
Um ! Where are you going ? Hey !
What 's going on out there ?
It 's Um . He 's deaf as an adder .
I called him many times
but he kept paddling away .
Oh my goodness !
What ? You were saying ?
Aren 't you ashamed ?
Standing there naked .
Everyone can see .
I was just glad ,
seeing a friend .
Perhaps he was scared .
Thought you were some hungry demon .
Mak !
Child is a fetter to the neck
Wealth is a fetter to the hands
Wife is a fetter to the feet
Rest in peace , Nak .
Father ! Father ! Yesterday I went fishing and saw Mak .
He must be living with Nak .
Heaven forbid !
Did he know ?
Oeb !
It 's me , Mak .
She 's been dead for three days .
You never told me .
Well , she died the day you arrived .
I was so happy you were home .
I completely forgot .
How did she die ?
Why was her body just left in there ?
While you were gone ,
there was a cholera outbreak . Many people died .
Oeb was infected .
Then relapsed for two days before she died .
People in the neighborhood
started moving away one by one .
I was afraid too .
Daeng was just an infant .
He could get infected .
So , I had to leave her like that .
From now on , please don 't go anywhere near that place .
I don 't want you to get infected .
Please !
I 'm scared ! Here 's your ring .
Take it back .
Oh la hey ...
Hey ...
Playful boat
Floats on the water
Magnificent
And great in measures
Anchored
To the pier
Waiting for passengers
To get on board
The prow faces ...
Come on !
Hurry up !
Honor to the Blessed One
The Exalted One The Fully Enlightened One
The sturn turns its back ...
to Pak Nam ...
Don 't you cry .
Nak .
I was looking for you .
Here you are . Pounding rice .
Why are you up ?
Go back to sleep .
What about you ?
Why are you pounding rice at this hour ?
Just do it in the morning .
We 're running out of rice .
I 'm afraid it 's not going to be enough for your breakfast .
Oh dear !
You should have told me before dark .
I would do it .
It 's alright .
It 's just ...
I want to take care of you .
I ...
don 't know how much time I have left .
If anything happens ...
Nak .
Why would you say that ?
You sound like you are leaving me .
Mak ...
Mak .
I love you so much .
In this life ,
I will never leave you .
But I 'm afraid ...
Nak .
What are you afraid of ?
I never thought of leaving you .
We will always be together
till death do us apart , Nak .
Come on .
Let 's go back to bed .
Ouch !
I 'll find some woods to fix it tomorrow .
Why are there rats all over the place ?
What are you doing down there ?
I 'm looking for an ax .
I 'm going to get some wood to fix the stairs .
It 's stuck on the post . Don 't you see it ?
Hey ! Um !
Um ! When did you come here ?
Hey ! Take it easy . How have you been ?
What about Yuean ?
Well ? Um .
Mak .
What 's the matter with you ?
You 're acting suspicious .
Mak , I have something to tell you .
You listen to me carefully .
What is it ?
Why don 't you just spit it out ?
You don 't have to make it complicated , Um .
Mak , your wife has been dead for a long time .
Ha ! Um !
What are you trying to do ?
Pulling a prank on me ?
I 'm not . It 's the truth .
Nak died during childbirth many months ago .
That 's enough , Um .
You crossed the line .
You son of a bitch accusing my wife of being dead ?
- This is not funny . - Mak , I 'm not lying .
Nak died while giving birth . Everybody knew .
- Except you , cause you weren 't here . - Um !
You liar ! I live with my wife and son . And you knew it .
How dare you lie to me ?
You think I 'm an idiot ?
Yes , you live with the ghosts every damn day . Don 't you realize ?
You 'd better stop right now !
If you are not my friend ,
I will beat the hell out of you !
Mak , I 'm not lying .
I swear on my life .
I tied her body with my own hands .
Um , do you hear that ? That 's my baby crying .
Yes , that baby 's a ghost .
Um ! You bastard !
Damn you ! You monster !
You call my baby a ghost !
- I 'm going to kill you ! - Alright ! Do it !
Go ! Get out of my face !
You and I , we 're not friends !
Don 't you dare come anywhere near me again . Go !
Fine !
I tried to warn you .
But you didn 't believe me . Then go on , live with the ghosts .
What 's wrong ?
He 's crying so loud .
Nothing . He was just crying for his mom .
He likes to be near me .
Or else , he starts crying .
Have you got the wood ?
No .
I ran into Um .
I was glad to see him but that bastard ...
He acted so strange , talking nonsense .
- What an idiot . - Um ...
What did he say ?
He said that you died during childbirth .
Wicked tongue !
Called you and our baby ghosts .
I just lost it . I punched him and chased him a way .
What 's the matter with him ?
He was ordained .
When did he become such a liar ?
It 's just weird .
What ?
You 're crying ?
Nak , why are you crying ?
You 'd been away too long .
Folks around here
started gossiping and accusing me .
Called me this and that to the point that I ...
I don 't want to go out anymore .
Why would they do that ?
They hate me .
They accused me of having an affair while you 're away .
They said Daeng wasn 't your baby .
Called me an adulteress .
They made up stories to harass me all the time .
Damn it !
You were pregnant before I was conscripted .
They all knew .
How could they accuse you like that ?
I don 't really know .
They bullied me . They hate on me .
Even Tid Um .
He was like a family to us .
Now he 's just like the rest of them .
It hurt so bad .
Nak .
Don 't feel so down .
Those people have wicked minds .
It 's not your fault .
No matter what they say ,
I will never believe it .
You don 't have to care .
Those foul-mouthed people .
I 'll kill them
if I see them .
Nak ...
Damn it ! Yuean ! Stop crying for heaven 's sake !
You want that ghost to kill me , you bitch ?
Then why did you put a foot in your mouth ?
I told you not to meddle with them .
Why didn 't you listen ?
Now what ?
If she knows ,
she will definitely kill you !
Shut up , Yuean !
Why can 't you just shut up ?
Stop wishing me death !
- Damn it ! - Isn 't it true ?
You messed with the ghost .
Tonight , she 'll come to get you .
- Um ! - Come on , Nak !
Come get me ! I 'll kill you with my sword !
- Nak ! You bitch ! - Don 't .
- Come on ! - Don 't say it !
- Come on ! Nak ! - She 'll come for real !
Come on now !
- Don 't go ! - Come break my neck !
- Please don 't go ! - I 'm not afraid of you !
Nak ! I 'm not afraid .
Come on !
- Walk faster . - I 'm walking fast . Don 't you see ?
- Faster than that . - It 's dark . I can barely see .
You 'll get scorned if you 're back late . I 'll laugh at you .
- You talk so much . Just go . - Aye .
Come on ! Hurry !
Get on the boat .
- Chiak , row smoothly . - Aye .
- It doesn 't move . - Take a look at it , you fool !
Aye .
Ghost !
- Help ! Ghost ! - It 's a ghost !
- Anybody ! Help ! - It 's a ghost !
Novice ! Wait ! Help me please !
Calm down .
Hey ! One at a time .
How can I know what 's going on ?
Father , Nak 's getting more violent .
She 's killed so many people .
We have to stop her . Otherwise ...
- more people will die . - What 's your plan ?
I think we have to find a shaman
to vanquish her spirit for good .
I don 't want any more deaths .
But Father , this shaman has a great reputation .
He has defeated evil spirits . Many people go to him .
It will work this time , Father .
Think carefully . Don 't be reckless .
- Think before you do anything . - There 's no time for thinking !
It was Mee yesterday and then Um .
I won 't just wait around
to get killed .
We all prepared .
Tonight 's the night .
We 're going to burn her house to the ground .
Take it easy , In .
If you burn the place , what about Mak ?
If he listens and steps away ,
we let him live .
But if he 's so determined to live with the ghosts ,
then ...
we 'll burn them all together .
Hey !
Who 's coming with me ?
- Get up now . - I 'm in .
Mak ! Mak !
Mak .
Father .
What brings you here ? Please come in .
Here please .
- Are you alone ? - Yes .
Nak went out to find water spinach . She 'll be back soon .
You must be tired .
Please have some water and betels .
Please .
I 'm fine . Thank you .
How are you , Father ?
It 's been such a long time .
I was going to visit you but didn 't get a chance .
Busy with kid and wife .
Mak , I came here to see you today
because I have something to tell you .
Yesterday ...
Tid Um told you , but you didn 't believe him .
It 's true , Mak .
- What 's true ? - About Nak .
She died during childbirth .
I can confirm it .
You 've live with the ghosts .
Do you know that ?
Father !
You 're a monk ! Why do you tell a lie ?
I live with them day and night .
How can they be the ghosts ?
Here 's my child sleeping in his crib .
See for yourself .
Does he look like a ghost to you ?
Mak , listen to me for once .
Nak is really dead .
Everybody knew .
I know . Know that you people ...
hate her so much ,
that you keep accusing her .
Um was one of them .
I lost it . I beat him up before he ran away .
Do you know that Um is dead ?
- He 's dead ? - That 's right .
Nak broke his neck last night .
- Because he told you about her . - This is insane !
Why are you talking nonsense ?
If you weren 't a monk ,
I 'd kick you out of here .
Alright .
I came all the way just to tell you .
If you don 't believe me , fine .
But if you want to see it with your own eyes ,
concentrate . Remind yourself of Buddha 's virtues .
Bend over and look between your legs . You 'll see the truth .
What ? You 're leaving ?
Wait a little longer .
Nak will be back soon .
So , you 'll see if she 's a ghost .
I 'd rather not . Come on . Let 's go .
Hey ! We 're here !
The shaman has arrived .
Yuean ! He 's here .
Please come in and have some drinks .
Choei , go get him some water right away !
Novice , get my stuff in my bag .
Yes , sir .
You two .
We should continue this later .
I have some urgent business
to attend to today .
We 'll discuss it later .
Where are you going ?
Phra Khanong .
Move !
Chiak ! Move over ! Let me sleep here !
- Hey ! I 'm not Chiak . - Oh ! Father ?
Here ! Drink it !
Drink it all up . You over there !
Drink it !
Tonight ,
I 'm going to take all of you
to burn that house down to the ground !
You coming with me ?
- Yes ! - Kill them !
Kill them !
May all dangers be dispelled
Hey ! Let 's go !
- Go ! - Go ! Go !
If you want to see it with your own eyes , concentrate .
Remind yourself of Buddha 's virtues and look between your legs .
Mak ...
Mak ! Get out of that house !
Mak ! Did you hear me ?
Burn it down !
How far would you push me ?
I 've never done anything to you .
Why do you mess with my family ?
Nak ! You 're a ghost !
But sleep with a man !
And you keep killing people .
I 'm going to destroy you .
I just want to live with my husband and my child .
I never killed anyone . Those people ...
died by their own karma because they tried to ruin our family .
That 's not on me .
Fine .
Tonight , you started it .
You burned my house .
I 'll show you how menacing
I can be .
What now ?
Hurry up ! Yes , that 's good !
Come on ! Everyone !
Yes ! Keep going !
Everybody , keep going !
Don 't just stand around !
Get it up there ! You get inside !
Pass the holy threads around in circle .
Everybody ! Hurry !
Come here .
Bind up the holy threads . Sit inside the circle .
Get inside . We 'll start chanting .
Take a seat ! Where 're you going ? Sit here .
Honor to the Blessed One
The Exalted One
The Fully Enlightened One ...
For the third time To the Buddha I go refuge ...
For the third time To the Sangha I go refuge ...
He has freed himself From the snares of Mara , the evil one
Multitudes who could be led to security
A Buddha , a Sugata , one freed
He has freed himself From the snares of Mara
The evil one ...
To the Buddha , highest excellence My head I bow down ...
By this power May you be triumphantly successful
And all dangers , may they be destroyed
The Dhamma that is like The teacher 's banner
Showing the world the path of purity
Upholding the Dhamma Leading out of samsara
Well practice Conducive to happiness and peace
To the Dhamma 's highest excellence
My head I bow down
Cleaver of delusion And calmer of fiery passion
May you be triumphantly successful And all dangers , may they be destroyed
- The army of the true Dhamma ... - It 's a ... ghost !
- ... is victor in the world over evil ... - Ghost ... Nak 's ghost !
Everyone , come back here ! Resume your chant !
Don 't be afraid . Keep chanting .
My head I bow down
Mak ...
Nak , scaring monks is a sin .
Don 't do this . Be gone .
Let 's not torment him .
Father .
- Let my husband go and I leave . - I can 't .
You 're a ghost .
Don 't interfere with humans .
I listen to no one .
You all want to separate my family .
Even a monk !
Let my husband go !
Then you will see .
Keep chanting .
Mak ...
Come back to your child ,
your wife .
Don 't you love me anymore ?
Mak ...
Please , come back .
I have nothing left .
Nak .
Mak !
Don 't step out .
To the Dhamma 's highest excellence My head I bow down
- He has freed himself from the snares ... - Mak ...
- To the Buddha , my head I bow down ... - Mak ...
The Dhamma that is like The teacher 's banner
He has freed himself from The snares of Mara , the evil one
Multitudes who could be led to security
To the Buddha , highest excellence My head I bow down
By this power May you be triumphantly successful
And all dangers May they be destroyed
The Dhamma ...
Hey ! Hey ! We can stop now .
Nak is gone .
My chanting 's still sacred .
Father ! Father !
We got a big trouble !
- What is it , Bua ? - It 's Toon and his friends .
They dug up Nak 's grave .
That shaman was with them too .
They 're doing something with the corpse .
- Oh , hell no ! - Nak !
Mak ! Don 't go ! Someone stop him !
Damn it ! Mak !
Go to that place
Nak !
Stop him !
If anyone hurts my wife , you have to do it over my dead body .
Nak ... Nak ...
Take him away .
Bring the corpse up here .
Don 't let him interrupt my ritual .
And never return .
Let me go ! Let me go !
Don 't hurt her !
No !
Hey !
What are you doing ? Stop it right now !
Nak .
Hey ! Wait !
Nak , don 't do it .
Somdet wants you
and everyone to step aside .
Don 't let anyone come near until he 's done .
The Lords of men , the Buddhas went up To their victorious throne
Conquered the evil one Together with his army and vehicles ...
Sika , let us have a conversation .
- Mak ? Is Mak here ? - I am .
Somdet wants you to join him .
You should say farewell to your wife .
Look at him .
Daeng is sleeping so peacefully .
Nak ...
My dear Nak .
Mak ...
I was blessed with such a short life .
I have to follow Somdet
to practice spiritual cultivation
until all my karma is paid off .
Hereafter ,
I won 't be able to take care of you ...
ever again .
Mak ...
Nak
The two of us
must have been blessed
only this far .
In the next life ,
I wish for us to be born to be husband and wife again .
Mak ...
Mak .
Let her go . It 's time .
Mak ...
- Nak ... - Mak ...
Mak .
Go to that place and never return
Om .
Who 's the abbot of Wat Mahabut ?
I am .
Be blessed .
I confined Nak 's spirit
in the bone of her forehead .
I will carry it with me .
From now on ,
she will not cause anyone harm .
Please arrange her funeral ,
along with the others .
Yes , sir .
Then I can go now .
Be blessed .
Since then , nobody has heard of Nak 's
vengeful spirit ever again .
Somdet Phra Putthacharn To
made a girdle brooch out of her forehead bone
to secure his waistband which he wore till the last day of his life .
It is believed that after he passed away ,
the relic from her forehead
came into the possession of His Royal Highness Prince Chumbhorn
and was handed down to many others .
Nobody knew exactly who owned the relic .
Nowadays , the relic in which her spirit confined
is long lost .
Only the story of her undying love
and devotion to her husband remains .
Her story has been immortalized to this day .
Subtitle translation by Suganya Pankote